This is my kitchen table and it's also
my filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind I've often thought
was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
While I watch your interview with Coach,
I know how to do something.
I've learned in doing my interviews, how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much he wanted.
He said to 50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence to have
something I'd like to sell and how they
stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
the only the second wealthiest man in
the world Is that right?
I think it's fair to say that I'm not an
expert on beauty or cosmetics, but I had
a chance racing to sit down with
somebody who is an expert, Bobbi Brown.
She launched the iconic company Bobbi
Brown Cosmetics a number of years ago.
And in 2020, she launched another
company called Jones Road Beauty.
I had a chance to sit down with her
recently to talk about all of this and
learned a lot more about beauty than I
knew before.
Let's talk about the cosmetics world,
which is not a world that I'm that
familiar with.
When you built your initial company, it
was, you know, a gigantic success.
What was it like starting all over
again?
One day you're in a big company, one big
parent, and then you have to start all
over again.
You know, it was really exciting and
invigorating.
I felt like a young kid again when I
started Jones Road, and right before we
launched, I definitely had a sudden
like, you know, like emotion of saying,
Oh, what if I'm a one hit wonder?
I was a little scared, but then I just
threw it up into the wind and went for
it.
Well, I can understand why you would
have called your first company, Bobbi
Brown, since that's your name, but Jones
Road, where that name come from?
Well, I sold the rights to Bobbi Brown,
to Estee Lauder when we sold the
company, so I couldn't use it again.
And why would I want to do something
that I've done before?
So we needed a name because I wanted to
launch Jones Road the day my 25 year
non-compete was up.
It was in 2020, a week before the
presidential elections.
And so I needed a name and I didn't have
one.
And I was driving to the Hamptons with
my husband.
My head was down on Waze, and I looked
down.
I saw Jones Road and he said, I said,
Jones Road Beauty.
He said, I like it.
And that's how it became Jones Road.
Now, in my business, sometimes I'm
familiar with non competes, but I never
really heard of a 25 year non-compete.
That's unusually long, isn't it?
You know, I didn't know because when we
sold the company and my husband said,
The deal is done, however they want you
to sign a 25 year non-compete.
I was around 34 years old and I never
heard of a non-compete, let alone
thought about a 25 year one.
But I thought to myself, Well, it's not
a problem because I'm not going to want
to work when I'm in my sixties.
So in the cosmetics world, the Giants
over the years have been a leaner.
RUBENSTEIN Not related to me, right?
Let's say Elizabeth Arden.
Elizabeth Arden.
Charles Revson.
Max Factor.
Yeah.
Let's see who else.
I say Lauder.
And these were people that all invented
something novel all the time.
Yes.
And in your case, you kind of invented.
What would you say?
I revolutionized natural looking makeup
because it was not popular at all.
You know, where foundations used to be
white and then painted in cheekbones and
all this artificial color.
Women look better when they came in with
no makeup.
Then after they had, like, a full on
makeover.
So I started making products that were
easy to apply and just made you look
better.
Like it was not complicated to me.
Well, let's talk about why people put
makeup on.
I personally believe that women wear
makeup to feel better.
However you choose to wear your makeup,
there's many different styles.
I think it is such an amazing thing to
be able to make yourself look and feel
better.
So for me, it's the way you feel even
more than the way you look, if that
makes sense.
I like a more natural makeup.
There are plenty of makeup brands that
cater to women that like a very strong
aesthetic.
That's just not me or Jones Road.
So it really does depend.
What age do you think girls or young
women should put makeup on?
I'm a young granddaughter.
Seven.
At what age is she going to come and say
she needs makeup?
Well, I think that young girls are
always love watching their moms put
makeup on.
They love the colors.
I have a three year old granddaughter.
Lily is quite good with the lip gloss
and puts, you know, my miracle balm on
my cheek.
Does she wear to school?
No, but it's, you know, it's going to be
in her blood.
So I don't think it's ever a big deal.
However, I've written two books about
teenage girls, and the only time I ever
tell, you know, mothers to really pay
attention.
If your kids are doing things like
putting black lipstick on and looking,
you know, Goth, you might want to just,
you know, stop for a minute and check
and say, you know, are they okay?
So who did who is the biggest customer
for makeup?
Is it women who are, I'd say, in their
teenage years?
Women in their twenties, their thirties,
the forties and fifties?
What age group is the biggest customer
for cosmetics?
Well, I think any woman is a customer
for cosmetics of any age.
Jones Road, our target audience is 30.
You know, just in the sixties and some
seventies.
But I think it is definitely changing
now.
The big thing are, is makeup for young
girls.
I don't understand.
I don't think seven and eight and nine
year old girls should worry about what's
in their skin care products.
But there's so much on social media now
that it's becoming a thing.
Let's talk about social media.
Some people say that influencers on
social media are driving people to buy
their beauty products.
Is that true?
100% true.
But you know, the great thing about
social media, it's a free way to market
your products.
We're back in the day.
You know, you had a spend a ton of money
and do advertising in this new world.
It's much easier to get your messages
out there.
I wanted to share my three favorite
products.
It's hard to choose.
It's like, which of my kids do I like
best?
It depends what day it is.
Cosmetics and beauty products are sold
today.
Or is it mostly online through Amazon,
or is it that big retailers like
Walmart?
I mean, there's definitely different
distributions.
My first brand was in higher end stores.
We launched in Bergdorf.
Then we were in Saks and Kendall's, and
by the time I left the company, we had
just started opening Macy's stores.
And that's how businesses grow is
distribution.
Jones Road has been following a
different playbook.
We are direct to consumer.
Probably 85% of our business is direct
to consumers through our own site just
online.
And now we have ten or 11 retail stores.
We're in one account department store,
Liberty in London.
Well, some people say that the price of
cosmetics and makeup and beauty care
products is relatively high because the
cost of packaging and the cost of
advertising.
Is that a big factor in the pricing of
your products?
Not my products.
Not our products.
That is a big factor.
You know, I come from a brand that spent
a lot of money on packaging and
marketing and and teams.
Jones Road is a different playbook.
We spend money on marketing, but we
don't spend a ton of money on our
packaging.
Our formulas are top notch, but our
packaging is more simple so we can keep
the costs down.
Where are your products made?
They're mostly made in the US, a lot of
them in New Jersey.
They the pencils like.
All cosmetics.
Pencils are made in Germany.
Our brushes are made in Italy.
You know, our packaging comes from Asia,
not China.
Mostly it comes from Taiwan and other
places.
So let's talk about for a moment the
business of cosmetics generally.
It's a business that's now really
largely controlled by large public
corporations.
I mean, your company is not public yet,
but is it mostly the large companies
that are doing the business of selling
these products?
It's definitely mostly large companies.
And, you know, most founders start these
businesses for one reason to sell.
I mean, Jones Road, I mean, I never
thought about selling Bobbi Brown
cosmetics until we got, you know,
Leonard, we had other people call.
It was never in my mind that that is
something you would do.
And so now I know eventually someone,
the right person will come.
And honestly, it's like, this is my
passion and it's what I do.
So the trick in makeup is to look like
you don't have a lot of makeup.
Yes.
What is the No makeup?
Makeup look.
Well, it's choosing colors that work
with your skin tone that don't make you
too pale and don't make you too bright.
And if you are someone that is going to
wear a little bit of powder on camera, I
would probably just give you a little
bit.
And you're not going to look like you're
wearing it.
And by the way, it's not supposed to
feel like you're wearing it.
Wow.
Like, look.
Look at how good you look.
So people are going to come up to me in
the next couple of minutes and say, Wow,
you look so great.
Have you been on a vacation?
Then I've done my job.
So what am I looking at here?
This is the famous product that started
it all.
This is called Miracle Balm.
And what you do, it's a skincare and
makeup and one.
And what it is, is you dip your finger
in it.
You take it like this.
Pat it on your cheeks.
It gives you color.
It gives you a glow.
Use it on your neck.
You can even use it on your body.
Comes in all colors.
And this is a miracle to most women
because it adds moisture and color to
the skin when there's new product.
Do you have to look at every new product
and approve it before it goes out?
I don't want to call myself a
micromanager, but I date the product.
I work with the team.
I approve.
And then I'm the one, you know, a year
later that says, oh, something shifted.
What happened?
So, yes, I am I am very involved.
Let's talk about how you got into this
business.
So were you born Chicago, suburbs of
Chicago, and what did your parents do?
They were 20 and 21 when I was born.
My dad, a lawyer.
My mom was always a homemaker.
And by the time they were 25, there were
three of us that lived in the house, you
know, three, three kids.
Okay.
And so where did you go to school?
I went to Nutria High school, big high
school and very famous high school in
Winnetka, Illinois.
Right.
Winnetka and Wilmette.
And really what I think really taught me
a lot about life was being around my
grandparents, Papa Sam, who came from
the Ukraine, who came here not knowing
anyone.
And by the time he was, you know, in his
elder years, he was very known in
Chicago as Cadillac Sam.
He sold cars to all the big guys and
some of the gangsters.
Meyer Lansky, Al Capone and work was
everything to Papa, followed by his
family.
And so that's really what raised me.
So you graduated from our new career
high school, right?
Then what did you do?
I graduated six months early to follow a
boyfriend went to University of
Wisconsin at Oshkosh because there was
no way I was getting into university.
University of Wisconsin in Madison.
I didn't have the grades.
I was there six months and then
transferred to University of Arizona
with all of my friends from high school,
because school for me was about fun and
not about what I was going to learn.
And at the end of the year, I told my
mom I was going to drop out and she
said, You can't.
You have to go to college.
She never did.
Mom, it's so boring.
And she said, Forget about anything.
Forget what you want to do.
If today's your birthday, you could do
anything you want to do, what would you
want to do?
And I said, I don't know.
Maybe go to Marshall Fields and play
with makeup.
She said, That's it.
Why don't you be a makeup artist?
I said, I don't want to go to beauty
school.
She said, I'm sure there's a college
somewhere.
And through a friend of my dad's, I
found Emerson College in Boston, and
they let me design my own major in
makeup.
That's Emerson.
Emerson.
All right.
And she majored in theatrical makeup,
right?
With a minor in photography.
That's a very unusual combination.
It was my two things I liked.
All right, So then you graduated?
Yes.
And then what'd you do?
So I got a waitressing job.
I lied to get the job because I had no
experience.
And I did that for a year.
And then I moved to New York.
I didn't know anyone.
I opened up the Yellow Pages and looked
up makeup models, and I just started
cold calling people.
And somehow I figured out how to put a
portfolio together.
And I started working as a freelance
makeup artist.
Really, the main thing I wanted was to
be in fashion.
So I did a lot of fashion shows.
I eventually, you know, did all the
magazines.
I got a Vogue cover.
You know, I started to get a name for
myself.
And then lo and behold, while I was
working, I also somehow was a frequent
guest on Oprah Winfrey to go on there
and do makeup.
And I became a regular on the Today
Show, talking about makeup, talking
about makeup, which I did for 14 years,
never once talked about my products or
my brand.
I was the expert.
It makes you confident and comfortable
so you could do anything in the world
you want to do.
When did you start Bobbi Brown Cosmetics
started?
Bobbi Brown Cosmetics When I
married my husband and we moved to
Montclair, New Jersey,
because I didn't want to be in New York
City.
And then I just had this idea.
I didn't want to travel anymore for work
because.
Being a freelance makeup artist, you're
always on a plane going to some exotic
place.
And I just said, you know, why don't I,
you know, think of something else?
I met a chemist at a shoot and told him
how much I hated lipstick that was in
the market and what I was looking for.
And he said, I can make it for you.
So he did.
He made me a lipstick.
And I thought, Wow, this is like,
amazing.
I bet I could sell it to my friends, to
models.
And I started doing that.
So you ultimately started a company
which had ten different shades of
lipstick, right?
Mm hmm.
And I sold them out of my house, and my
husband would mail them.
They didn't even have a box.
They were in an envelope.
So they were, you know, very indie.
We put the ingredients on a card and
started shipping them.
And then one day we were at a party and
I said, you know, thank the hostess for
inviting us.
I had never met her before, and she said
she was a fan of mine.
I'm like, Oh, you know who I am?
That's so nice.
I said, What do you do?
She said, Obama cosmetics buyer Bergdorf
Goodman.
I said, Oh, I sell these cosmetics out
of my house.
And she agreed to take them and sell
them at Bergdorf.
And the venture capitalist didn't come
along and said, We'd like a piece of
your company and we'll give you some
money.
Or did you just, you know, we totally
financed it ourselves.
And, you know, I didn't know those
people back then.
We had people reach out to us, you know,
when our business started to grow, they
wanted to buy us.
We weren't for sale until we got a call
from Leonard Lauder because I fell madly
in love at first sight.
I didn't know.
Leonard, a very impressive person.
So he convinced you to sell the company,
right?
I think we were maybe four and a half
years in business when we sold the
company to Leonard.
And so when you did that, you kept the
name Bobbi Brown Cosmetics, or did you
say, Well, they bought it?
I mean, it was called Bobbi Brown Cosmo.
But it was but it was still called that
Bobbi Brown Cosmetics and didn't stay
with stay long.
We were the second brand they bought
that they didn't make internally.
And Leonard's thing was to run
everything independently.
Everything about Leonard was supporting
the founder, supporting the integrity of
the brand.
When we first joined Estee Lauder, I'll
never forget they wanted our lipsticks
to be made in there in their lab.
And so it was, you know, we started the
project and it was terrible.
I couldn't recreate them properly.
And finally Leonard got involved.
He said, absolutely not.
If you you know, if you do not.
If you change them, women are going to
know.
So, no, we will work with the lab that
makes your lipsticks.
But Bobbi Brown Cosmetics, did they sell
the same place that Estee Lauder would
sell, which is the big department store?
Well, when Leonard approached me, we
were the number one line in Neiman
Marcus and Bergdorf.
So we were beating Estee Lauder in the
store.
And we did not even have a full line.
It was a it was really a phenomenon.
So as you work through Estee Lauder for
some 20 plus years, you were building
the brand, the building, the brand.
And now when you left Estee Lauder, you
decided to start a new company, right?
Right.
I, I left Estee Lauder.
Did I quit or get fired?
To me, I got fired.
So why would they hire you?
Because there was a lot of angst in the
year or so before I left.
And it's all in my biography, so or in
my memoir.
So it's all out there.
It was tough.
I mean, Leonard wasn't as involved in
when, you know, in the company and there
was a new, you know, CEO and a new, you
know, a lot of new things were happening
and it was not a good time at all.
And so
it was it was honestly, really tough.
And it's the best thing that ever
happened to me getting fired, if you
want know the truth.
So because now you could start your own
company once a non-compete, right?
Yes, but why not say, Look, I already
conquered the cosmetics world once.
Why do I have to do it a second time?
Why wasn't planning on doing it like I
didn't?
You know, when it first happened, I had
no.
It was 22 years of having a full
calendar.
Full schedule.
Cars follow me around.
PR people, you know, with clipboards
following me around, and all of a sudden
it was gone.
I didn't know what I was going to do,
and I didn't think I was going to start
another cosmetics company.
If you could give advice to the 25 year
old Bobbi Brown, what would the advice
be You wish you had known then something
you know now?
She wouldn't have listened, but I would
have told her to chill and relax.
It's all going to be fine.
You.
Now your new brand is focused more on, I
would say, health and wellness to some
extent.
Mm hmm.
So why is it healthier to put on Jones
Jones Road Road than Bobby Brown?
Or what's different about it that makes
it healthier?
Well, when I started Jones Road, I was
on my own path to really being the
healthiest version of myself.
So I went back to school, got my degree
as a health coach.
I started only eating organic when I
can.
And I started cleaning up, you know,
what chemicals are in my products.
And when I finally decided to really try
to create a new beauty product, I was
not going to do a traditional product.
I really was curious if it was even
possible to create something out of
clean because the market has had shifted
where women wanted clean makeup.
So I didn't do it because I didn't
believe in traditional.
I did it because I didn't know if it was
possible to do, and I proved that it
was.
And can you tell if they're wearing one
of your products?
Usually, if there's a nice sheen and a
highlight on the cheek, I could you
know, and I know and often people come
up to me and they, like, you know, point
to something and say, Dusty Rose,
Sunkist, and you say, Buy more.
Now I say, Great.
So today, if I wanted to start a
company, I wanted to be Bobbi Brown, and
I want to start a cosmetics company.
What would you recommend that I do?
Well, first of all, there's nothing easy
in life in general.
But if you're a kid that is just coming
out of college or even business school,
I'd say go work for someone for a year.
You know, go really, like, learn what
you can before you start something and
maybe start dating and thinking what
your company would be before you decide
to do it.
Don't start with a deck and investment.
Like people make that mistake.
Start with a product.
So today, if you are going to build this
company out, is it your goal to
ultimately find another Estee Lauder or
to just take it public or just keep it
private owned by the family?
You know, I don't know.
I you know, I'm 68 years old.
It's been five years.
You know, the business is growing.
We do get a lot of calls from probably
people that you have lunch and dinners
with.
We're self-funded.
I don't need any money.
We have enough cash in the bank to do
what we want to do, you know?
But I don't know what's going to happen
in the future.
I'm not opposed to the right situation
on something.
I just don't know what it is.
And that's okay.
And do you try to expand your product
outside the United States at this point,
or is it too small right now to go
outside the United?
No, we are available in Canada.
We are available in the U.K.
and now we're available in Europe.
So,
you know, we're not freestanding stores
yet.
I really want a freestanding store and
in London, because that's one of our
biggest markets.
So what are the most important beauty
secrets you would give to somebody two
or three beauty secrets?
Well, I would say, first of all, worry
about your inside more than your
outside.
Take care of your health.
Number two is worry about, you know,
your skin.
Don't smoke.
Wear sunscreen.
And and third, just wear makeup.
So it just makes you look better.
End of story.
Now, did your parents live to see your
success?
My father?
Yes.
My father is still alive.
My dad's 90.
He has.
Proven how proud he is of me.
He's told me and he he just he always
says, I know you're not done.
And I know I'm going to keep hearing
things.
So if you could give advice to the 25
year old Bobbi Brown, what would the
advice be?
You wish you had known then something
you know now?
She wouldn't have listened, but I would
have told her to chill and relax.
It's all going to be fine.
She wouldn't have listened because I
still haven't figured out how to chill
and relax.
Now, presumably, the most important
thing in life is personal happiness,
which is also the most elusive thing in
life.
So as a result of having built these
companies, I assume you're personally
very happy with what you're doing now.
I'm so incredibly lucky because I'm
married 37 years.
I still adore my husband.
I have three sons, two grandkids.
We are all very close.
And, you know, I have not only old
friends, I have new friends, people I've
just met.
So I feel very, very happy.
And my you know, John's Road is a very
young team, but they're my new posse.
While you're young, do worry about
legacies.
But what would you like your legacy to
ultimately be?
You know, I hope my legacy will be that
I was there to help people feel good
about themselves and teach people how to
be confident.
Because I've figured out the secret of
confidence.
All it is is feeling comfortable in your
skin.
You.